Register of the Commission for Relief in Belgium (1940-1945) Records, 1939-1947
Hoover Institution Archives
Commission for Relief in Belgium (1940-1945) Records,
1939-1947
XX402
Commission for Relief in Belgium (1940-1945)
17 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 8 envelopes (7.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and photographs, relating to efforts to provide civilian relief to Belgium and Luxembourg during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (17 reels).
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Food question.; World War, 1939-1945--Luxembourg.; Belgium.; Luxembourg.; International relief.; National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies.
Series Description
- OFFICE FILE, 1939-1947 (Boxes 1-5)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, printed matter and other materials relating to the operations of the Commission for Relief in Belgium. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1939-1946 (Boxes 6-12)
  Letters sent and received by the C.R.B. Includes correspondence with individuals, groups and organizations, the Belgian Embassy and Consulates in the United States, arranged chronologically and alphabetically by name of correspondent
- BELGIAN RELIEF FUND, 1940-1941 (Boxes 12-15)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, printed matter and other materials relating to the operations of the Belgian Relief Fund. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- BELGIAN GENERAL RELIEF COMMITTEE (WINTERHELP), 1940-1941 (Boxes 15-16)
  Correspondence, memoranda, publicity leaflets, reports, printed matter and other materials relating to the operations of the Belgian General Relief Committee (Winterhelp). Arranged alphabeticaly by physical form
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1945 (Boxes 16-17)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, clippings, printed matter and other materials, collected by the C.R.B. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1838-1941 (Box 18)
  Food map, leaflets, placards and posters issued by the C.R.B.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1940-1941 (Photo file)
  216 prints in 8 envelopes depicting relief operations of the C.R.B. in Belgium
Container List
- OFFICE FILE, 1939-1947
  - Appeal for aid (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Application forms for foreign and domestic relief activities (Folder 2)
  - By-laws (Folder 3)
  - Certificate of incorporation (Folder 4)
  - Chapters file
    - Connecticut
      - Danbury (Folder 5)
      - Fairfield County (Folder 6)
    - Diamond Industry (Folder 7)
    - Nebraska (Folder 8)
    - Notebaert, Sengier, Speciael (Folder 9)
    - Princeton (Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 11)
  - Contributions file (Folder 12-15)
  - Directors and members invitations and acceptances (Folder 16)
  - Financial records
    - General (Folder 17)
    - General (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Disbursements (Folder 2)
    - Luncheon expenses (Folder 3)
    - Receipts and disbursements (Folder 4)
    - Supplies purchased
      - 1940 (Folder 5)
      - 1941 (Folder 6)
    - Transfer of funds to Europe, 1940-1942 (Folder 7-8)
  - Liquidation file (Folder 9-10)
  - Liquidation file (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Meetings file
    - General
      - 1940 (Folder 2)
      - 1941 (Folder 3)
    - Directors
      - 1940
        - May 20 (Folder 4)
        - December 11 (Folder 5)
      - 1941 May 20 (Folder 6)
    - Executive Committee, 1940
      - July 11 (Folder 7)
      - December 11 (Folder 8)
    - Incorporators, 1940 May 20 (Folder 9)
    - Members, 1941 May 20 (Folder 10)
  - Organizational charts (Folder 11)
  - Permit for soliciting funds (Folder 12)
  - Press releases and publicity file (Folder 13)
  - Printed matter (Folder 14)
  - Regulations for the formation of chapters and committees (Folder 15)
  - Reports (Box 4)
    - To Herbert Hoover. "Memorandum of Food Situation and Events Connected Therewith in Belgium, Brussels, 1940 May-July" (Folder 1)
    - To the U.S. Department of State
      - 1940 (Folder 2)
      - 1941 (Folder 3-4)
  - Signing authority forms
    - Guaranty Trust Company of New York (Folder 5)
    - Irving Trust Company (Folder 6)
    - National City Bank of New York (Folder 7)
  - Statement by H. Hoover, "An Experiment in Saving the Lives of 3,000 Destitute Adults and Children in Belgium," 1941 April 1 (Folder 8)
  - Subject file
    - Badges, buttons, pins (Folder 9)
    - Bundles for Britain (Folder 10)
    - Delaware filing fee (Folder 11)
    - Donations (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Foreign Policy Association luncheon, 1940 December 7 (Folder 5)
    - Hospital volunteers (Folder 6)
    - Insurance coverage (Folder 7)
    - Office equipment (Folder 8)
    - Orphans, Adoption of (Folder 9)
    - President's Committee on War Relief Agencies (Folder 10)
    - Statutory representation (Folder 11)
    - Supplies
      - Clothing (Folder 12)
      - Food (Folder 13)
    - Surety bonds (Folder 14)
    - Tax exemptions (Folder 15)
    - Visit to Belgium of the CRB Representatives, 1941 January 19-24 (Folder 16)
  - Miscellany (Folder 17)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1939-1946
  - Chronological file (Box 6)
    - 1940
      - May-June (Folder 1)
      - July-August (Folder 2)
      - September-December (Folder 3)
    - 1941
      - January-March (Folder 4)
      - April-November (Folder 5)
    - 1942 (Folder 6)
  - Alphabetical file
    - A (Folder 7)
    - B (Folder 8)
    - C (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - D (Folder 3)
    - E (Folder 4)
    - F (Folder 5)
    - G (Folder 6)
    - H (Folder 7-8)
    - I (Folder 9)
    - J (Folder 10)
    - K (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - L (Folder 2)
    - M (Folder 3-4)
    - N (Folder 5)
    - O (Folder 6)
    - P (Folder 7)
    - R (Folder 8)
    - S (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - T (Folder 4)
    - U-V (Folder 5)
    - W (Folder 6)
    - X-Z (Folder 7)
    - Allied Relief Fund, 1940 (Folder 8)
    - American Friends Service Committee, 1940 (Folder 9)
    - American Red Cross, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
    - Anderson, L. J., 1941 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Belgian Bureau, 1939-1940 (Folder 2)
    - Belgium. Ambassade (United States) (Folder 3)
    - Belgium. Consulat (New York) (Folder 4)
    - Belgium. Légation (Argentine) (Folder 5)
    - Belgium. Légation (Canada) (Folder 6)
    - Bordeaux Headquarters, 1940 (Folder 7)
    - Bove, Charles, 1941 (Folder 8)
    - British War Relief Society, 1940 (Folder 9)
    - Bronxville Community Forum, 1941 (Folder 10)
    - Brooklyn Republican Club, 1941 (Folder 11)
    - Brouha, Lucien, 1941 (Folder 12)
    - Brown, Crosby and Company, 1940 (Folder 13)
    - Brown, Milton M., 1940-1942 (Folder 14)
    - Brown, Milton M., Mrs., 1940-1941 (Folder 15)
    - Bryn Mawr College, 1941 (Folder 16)
    - Bundesen, Herman, 1941 (Folder 17)
    - Bundles for Britain, Inc., 1941 (Folder 18)
    - Canadian Committee, 1940 (Folder 19)
    - Carrel, Alexis, 1941 (Folder 20)
    - Chase National Bank, 1940-1941 (Folder 21)
    - Chautauqua Institution, 1941 (Folder 22)
    - Church of the Pilgrimage, 1941 (Folder 23)
    - Consolidated Edison Company, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Darnall, John P., 1940-1941 (Folder 2)
    - Deloitte, Plender, Griffiths, 1940-1942 (Folder 3)
    - Frederickson, Kirsten, 1941 (Folder 4)
    - Freiberg, Jacques, 1940 (Folder 5)
    - Galpin, Perrin, 1940 (Folder 6)
    - Garden Club of America, 1940 (Folder 7)
    - Gibson, Hugh, 1940-1941 (Folder 8)
    - Hamilton, B. Wallace, 1941 (Folder 9)
    - Henry, Bayard, Mrs., 1940 (Folder 10)
    - Hoover, Herbert C., 1940-1941 (Folder 11)
    - Hynes, John H., 1940 (Folder 12)
    - Irwin, Will, 1941 (Folder 13)
    - London Committee, 1940-1941 (Folder 14)
    - London Office, C.R.B., 1940-1941 (Folder 15)
    - L'Union Belge, 1940 (Folder 16)
    - Miller, James Alexander, 1941 (Folder 17)
    - Morris, Dave H., 1940 (Folder 18)
    - New York Council of Women, 1941 (Folder 19)
    - New York Telephone Company, 1940-1941 (Folder 20)
    - Refugees of England, Inc., 1940-1941 (Folder 21)
    - Rhode, Max Spencer, 1941 (Folder 22)
    - Richmond, Raymond, 1940-1941 (Folder 23)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1940 (Folder 24)
    - Sawtelle, Raymond, 1940-1941 (Folder 25)
    - Shattuck, Bangs and Davis, 1939-1942 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - United States. Department of State
      - 1939-1940 (Folder 2)
      - 1940-1941 (Folder 3)
      - 1942 (Folder 4)
    - United States. Internal Revenue Service, 1941-1946 (Folder 5)
    - Van der Straten-Ponthoz, Countess, 1940 (Folder 6)
    - Van der Straten-Ponthoz, R., 1940-1941 (Folder 7)
    - Van Loon, Hendrick, 1940 (Folder 8)
    - Vanderbilt, O. De Gray, 1940 (Folder 9)
    - Walsh, Edmund A., 1940 (Folder 10)
    - Wardwell, Allen, 1941 (Folder 11)
    - Watson, Benjamin, Mrs., 1940-1941 (Folder 12)
    - Whitlock, Brand, Mrs., 1940-1941 (Folder 13)
    - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1941 (Folder 14)
- BELGIAN RELIEF FUND, 1940-1941
  - Bulletins, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1940 (Folder 16)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - Cables, 1940
        - Incoming (Folder 17)
        - Outgoing (Folder 18)
      - Letters
        - 1940-1941 (Folder 19)
        - 1941 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Brown, Milton M., 1940 (Folder 3)
    - Kirby, Gustavus, 1940 (Folder 4)
    - Mitchell, P. V. G., 1940 (Folder 5)
    - Morris, Dave H., 1940-1941 (Folder 6)
    - Stevenson, Suzanne S., 1940 (Folder 7)
  - Financial statements (Folder 8)
  - Form letters (Folder 9)
  - Letter to C.R.B. members, n.d. (Folder 10)
  - Meetings file
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Directors, 1940 (Folder 12)
    - Incorporators, 1940 June 10 (Folder 13)
    - Temporary Coordinating Committee, 1940 June 4 (Folder 14)
  - Peninsula Chapter (Palo Alto, CA) file
    - General (Folder 15)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1940-1941 (Folder 16)
  - Stationery (Folder 17)
  - Subject file
    - Brasher, Rex (Folder 18)
    - Donations (Folder 19)
    - Fuel oil, munitions (Folder 20)
    - Lace sale, 1940 November-December (Folder 21)
    - Milling (Folder 22)
    - Moen, Lars (Folder 23)
    - Munitions. See Fuel oil, munitions
    - Office equipment (Folder 24)
    - Posters (Folder 25)
    - Speakers Bureau (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Supplies (Folder 2)
    - Warehouse facility (Folder 3)
  - Womens Division file
    - General (Folder 4)
    - Contribution receipts (Folder 5)
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - A-D (Folder 6)
        - E-L (Folder 7)
        - M-S (Folder 8)
        - T-Z (Folder 9)
    - Financial statements (Folder 10)
    - Inter-office memoranda (Folder 11)
    - Memorandum entitled "Clothing House for Belgium - Plan of Organization," n.d. (Folder 12)
    - Subject file
      - Belgian lapel pins and earrings (Folder 23)
      - Belgian lapel pins and earrings (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Building (328 Park Avenue, New York) (Folder 2)
      - Donations
        - Clothing (Folder 3)
        - Drycleaners, laundries (Folder 4)
        - Stores helping with (Folder 5)
      - Knitting (Folder 6)
      - Laymens League for Arts and Industries (Folder 7)
      - Social events
        - General (Folder 8)
        - La Guardia Field cocktail party, 1940 July 16 (Folder 9)
      - Village Fair for Refugee Children, 1940 July 9-13 (Folder 10)
- BELGIAN GENERAL RELIEF COMMITTEE (WINTERHELP), 1940-1941
  - General (Box 15, Folder 11-12)
  - Clippings (Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (Folder 14)
  - Interviews, speeches, statements (Folder 15)
  - Printed matter (Box 16)
    - General (Folder 1)
    - Secours d'Hiver, 1941, nos. 1, 3, 6, 7-9 (Folder 2)
    - Winterhulp, 1941, nos. 1, 3, 7, 9 (Folder 3)
  - Subject file
    - Belgium
      - Food rations, 1941 August-September (Folder 4)
      - Food supply (Folder 5-6)
    - Europe - Food production (Folder 7)
    - Save the Children International Union (Folder 8)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1945
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, clippings, printed matter and other materials
  - American Field Service in France (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Folder 10)
  - American Hospital in Paris (Folder 11)
  - American Relief Fund (Folder 12)
  - Belgians - United States (Folder 13)
  - Belgium - History - German occupation, 1940-1945 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Childrens Crusade for Childen (Folder 2)
  - Commission for Polish Relief (Folder 3)
  - Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies (Folder 4)
  - Cudahy, John (Folder 5)
  - Famine (Folder 6)
  - Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America (Folder 7)
  - Finnish Relief Fund (Folder 8)
  - France - History - German occupation, 1940-1945 (Folder 9)
  - Fundraising efforts (Folder 10)
  - Hippocratic Oath (Folder 11)
  - Jewish support of Belgian relief operations (Folder 12)
  - Leopold III, King of Belgium (Folder 13)
  - National Committee on Food for the Five Small Democracies (Folder 14)
  - Poster stamp (Folder 15)
  - Radio broadcasts, 1941 January-June (Folder 16)
  - Relief agencies (Folder 17)
  - Refugees (Folder 18-19)
  - Sponsors (Folder 20)
  - Steamship agents and brokers (Folder 21)
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - General (Folder 22)
    - Controlled mass-feeding of invaded territories (Folder 23)
  - Miscellany (Folder 24)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1938-1941
  - Food map illustrating and listing foodstuff exports and imports of various countries, 1938. Prepared by the C.R.B. (Box 18)
  - Leaflets, placards, and posters issued by the C.R.B., 1940-1941
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1940-1941
  - 81 prints depicting officers of the C.R.B. and Belgian Red Cross, and various dignitaries in Belgium, 1940-1941 (Envelope A-B)
  - 50 prints depicting preparations of clothing, food, and paperwork before distribution. Includes Belgian adults and children waiting in lines (Envelope C)
  - 36 prints depicting distribution of clothing and food to adults and children in Belgium, 1940 (Envelope D)
  - 6 prints depicting Belgian children (Envelope E)
  - 27 prints depicting various street scenes in Belgium (Envelope F)
  - 7 prints depicting interior scenes illustrating living conditions in Belgium (Envelope G)
  - 9 prints depicting posters and publicity placards issued by the C.R.B. (Envelope H)